Guide to the Benoit Mandelbrot Papers M1857
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Benoit Mandelbrot papers
circa 1932-2010
M1857
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
413.0 Linear feet (396 manuscript boxes; 3 half boxes; 79 cartons; 48 flat boxes; 1 card box; 10 map folders; 1 map tube)
The papers document the life and work of Benoit B. Mandelbrot, mathematician and pioneer of fractal geometry. The collection contains correspondence, research data, drafts and publications, administrative records, teaching material, photographs, artwork, audiovisual material, and computer media relating to Mandelbrot's education, professional career, and work in several organizations, principally at IBM's Thomas J. Watson Research Center and Yale University.
Mandelbrot, Benoit B.
Biographical Note
Benoit B. Mandelbrot was born in 1924 to a Lithuanian Jewish family in Warsaw, Poland. In 1936, the family fled the Nazis, moving first to Paris and then to southern France. After the war, Mandelbrot continued his studies at the École Polytechnique in Paris and then in the United States at the California Institute of Technology. He returned to France and completed a Ph.D. in Mathematics at the University of Paris in 1952. Mandelbrot spent most of his professional research career at IBM's Thomas J. Watson Research Center, beginning in 1958; with his appointment as an IBM Fellow in 1974, he was free to follow his personal inclination towards interdisciplinary research founded on applied mathematics.
Mandelbrot had begun to focus his attention on fractal mathematics during the 1960s, beginning with his article, "How Long is the Coast of Britain? Statistical Self-Similarity and Fractional Dimension," published in Science (1967). In this article he introduced fractals as part of the solution to a problem that had occupied his attention for some time: How to measure a curve as complex as a geographic coastline? He discussed two salient characteristics of fractals that applied to this problem: self-similarity and "fractional" dimensionality. Self-similarity referred to the persistence of patterns as an observer zoomed in or out of the visualization of a fractal set. Fractional geometry described the quality these sets had mathematically of being "fuzzier" than a line but never completely filling a plane. A few years later, in 1975, Mandelbrot introduced the term "fractal" to describe such mathematical sets. Over the course of his career, until his death in 2010, Mandelbrot encouraged the application of fractal geometry to fields ranging from engineering and medicine to finance, climate study, and art.
Mandelbrot first rendered a computer-generated image of the set that would be named after him at IBM's Thomas J. Watson Research Center in 1980. The computer plot produced by a software program revealed the distinctive image of a large vaguely heart-shaped object connected to a smaller spherical object and having a rough, fuzzy border. While this was neither the first mathematical study of this particular mathematical set nor the first visualization of it, Mandelbrot had developed an algorithm that would be the basis of subsequent computer programs used to study and visualize fractals.
Mandelbrot’s work was introduced to a wider readership with the publication of an article about the Mandelbrot Set in Scientific American (1985). Like many other results from applied and recreational mathematics, it appeared in A.K. Dewdney’s "Computer Recreations" column. Dewdney opened by describing Mandelbrot’s visualization of the set, announcing to his readers that "here is an infinite regress of detail that astonishes us with its variety, its complexity and its strange beauty." He described Mandelbrot’s work in fractal geometry and how the boundary of the Mandelbrot Set was a fractal exhibiting fractional dimensionality and the recursive quality of self-similarity. The article went on to describe how a computer program could function essentially as a microscope for this geometrical object, allowing the observer to examine its properties in exquisite detail, "like a tourist in a land of infinite beauty."[A. K. Dewdney, "Computer Recreations: A Computer Microscope Zooms in for a Look at the Most Complex Object in Mathematics," Scientific American, 253, Aug. 1985: 16-24.]
Mandelbrot wrote and edited a number of significant books describing his research into fractal geometry, including Fractals: Form, Chance and Dimension (1977) and The Fractal Geometry of Nature (1983). He was also the author of numerous articles and conference papers and received many awards and honorary degrees for his work.
After leaving IBM in 1987, he became a professor of Mathematics at Yale University, a position he held until his retirement in 2005.
His memoir, The Fractalist: Memoir of a Scientific Maverick, was published in 2012.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given by Aliette Mandelbrot to Stanford University, Special Collections in 2011, 2012, and 2013.
General note
The initials BBM are sometimes used in the guide for Benoit B. Mandelbrot.
Scope and Contents
The papers document the life and work of Benoit B. Mandelbrot, mathematician and pioneer of fractal geometry. The collection contains biographical material, personal and professional correspondence, drafts and typescripts for books and articles, subject files, and reprints. The collection also contains a significant amount of research data, including notes, plots, graphs, and computer-generated visualizations of fractals. Also included are teaching materials, administrative records, awards, and materials related to publicity events, such as posters and flyers announcing conferences and talks focusing on fractals or related topics. Other formats present in the collection include photographs and audiovisual and born-digital material. There is also an extensive amount of fractal and fractal-related artwork and artifacts.
Access to Collection
The collection is open for research except materials in Series 28: Restricted Material (boxes 327, 328, 329, 330, 495, 496). Restricted materials are closed until January 1, 2045.
The majority of audiovisual material in the collection has been digitally reformatted and is available to view in the Special Collections Reading Room.
Born-digital materials are still being processed and not yet open for research.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into 28 series:
Series 1. Personal/Biographical
Series 2. Course Work
Series 3. Personal Correspondence
Series 4. "Mail Files"
Series 5. Professional Correspondence
Series 6. Loose Correspondence
Series 7. Books
Series 8. Research Articles and Other Writings
Series 9. Working files/Research
Series 10. Professional Activities
Series 11. Data/Plots/Visualizations
Series 12. Plots/Graphs – rolls
Series 13. Interviews and Transcripts
Series 14. Teaching Material
Series 15. Certificates, Awards, and Diplomas
Series 16. Grant/Contract Administration
Series 17. Administrative Files
Series 18. Reprints and Subject Files
Series 19. Reprints by Mandelbrot
Series 20. Clippings
Series 21. Works by Others
Series 22. Publicity Material
Series 23. Artwork and Artifacts
Series 24. Photographic Material
Series 25. Music
Series 26. Audiovisual Material
Series 27. Computer Media/Born-digital Material
Series 28. Restricted Material
Mandelbrot, Benoit B.; Computer graphics.; Fractals in art; Fractals.; Julia sets; Mandelbrot sets; Mathematics--History--20th century.; Thomas J. Watson IBM Research Center
- Series 1. Personal/Biographical, 1930s-2013
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of the personal papers of Mandelbrot and his family, including civil status, naturalization, military and immigration documents. Also included are identification cards, calendars and biographical material such as Curricula Vitae, obituaries, and lists of publications. This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Photostat letter, 1877 (Box 500, Folder 3)
  - "Etat Civil - Parents" - includes originals and photocopies of BBM's parents' civil status documents such as naturalization records, identification cards, certificates, marriage documents), 1930s-1960s (Box 319, Folder 14)
  - BBM's legal/etat civil (civil status) documents - including naturalization records, originals and photocopies, 1930s-1980s (Box 319, Folder 15)
  - Military service - Batallion de l'Air 117 - Forces Armees Air (correspondence, memoranda, forms, notes, certificates), 1947-1950 (Box 319, Folder 16)
  - Brochures - "Trips through the west from Caltech 1949" (National Parks) (Box 319, Folder 17)
  - Legal/Etat Civil documents and correspondence, 1949-1973 (Box 302, Folder 3)
  - BBM's immigraion documents, 1940s (Box 319, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, exam results, identification information (documents reflect BBM's assumed name during World War II (Bernard Montel) as well as BBM's first name prior to naturalization (Baruch), 1940s-1950s (Box 319, Folder 19)
  - "Personal papers" - civil status documents, military service documents, identification cards, 1940s-1980s (Box 320, Folder 1)
  - Souveniers - "passports and the like" - identification cards, correspondence, circa 1940s-1990s (Box 320, Folder 2)
  - "Papiers Etat Civil" - France and US - original and photocopied documents including naturalization documents, passport, 1940s-2000s (Box 320, Folder 3)
  - Sketch of BBM in Paris by Joan, 1954 Jun 16 (Box 320, Folder 4)
  - "Sz [Szolem Mandelbrojt?] and Had and Granddad and other grandpap" (notes, writings), circa 1950s (Box 302, Folder 4)
  - Business and identification cards, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 320, Folders 6-7)
  - Letters documenting BBM's history of military service, 1950s-1960s (Box 320, Folder 5)
  - Lease, 1962 (Box 320, Folder 8)
  - Calendar, 1963-1964 (Box 320, Folder 9)
  - Immigration documents - BBM's housekeeper, 1960s (Box 320, Folder 10)
  - Daily Diary, 1970 (Box 320, Folder 11)
  - Daily Diary, 1971 (Box 320, Folder 12)
  - Pocket diaries/agendas and address books, 1975-2008 (Box 86)
  - "List of reviews, review essays, and comments, and summary scrapbook" 1982 Jan 11 (Box 320, Folder 13)
  - List of major reviews, review essays and comments, and summary scrapbook (edited drafts), 1983 May (Box 238, Folder 2)
  - Vita and publications, 1983 Aug (Box 238, Folder 3)
  - "List of major reviews of books and of feature stories they inspired, and summary scrapbook" (edited computer printout drafts), 1983-1984 (Box 320, Folder 14)
  - Vita and Publications, 1983-1984 (Box 320, Folder 15)
  - "Selected scientific achievements, cataloged by issue or by field" (heavily edited handwritten/computer printout drafts), 1984 (Box 320, Folder 16)
  - Lease, 1985 (Box 320, Folder 17)
  - "Books and Lectures by Benoit B. Mandelbrot: A Scrapbook of Excerpts from Reviews," 1987 (Box 320, Folder 18)
  - "Rachat Retraite" - pension buy-back, 1980s (Box 321, Folder 1)
  - Tree/Garden maintenence, circa 1980s (Box 322, Folder 6)
  - Identification cards - including IBM, driver's licence, immigration, memberships, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 321, Folder 2)
  - CV, 2001 Dec (Box 321, Folder 3)
  - Chronicle of meetings on fractal geometry, 2004 Jan (Box 321, Folder 4)
  - IBM 2007 Emeritus Contract - Benoit Mandelbrot (Box 321, Folder 5)
  - Obituaries - clippings, internet printouts, 2010 (Box 321, Folders 6-7)
  - Website updates - vita, publications, scrapbooks, review excerpts, handwritten notes, references, correspondence, circa 2010-2011 (Box 321, Folders 8-9)
  - Exhibition - "The Islands of Benoit Mandelbrot: Fractals, Chaos, and the Materiality of Thinking" - Bard Graduate Center, 2012 Sep 21 - 2013 Jan 27 (Box 321, Folder 15)
  - Autobiographical sketches, undated (Box 321, Folder 10)
  - Biographical material, undated (Box 321, Folder 11)
  - Blank letterhead and graph paper, undated (Box 321, Folder 12)
  - Cartoons - fractal-related, undated (Box 321, Folder 13)
  - CVs, undated (Box 321, Folder 14)
  - "Good quotes" undated (Box 322, Folder 1)
  - Essays and selecta, undated (Box 322, Folder 2)
  - Handwritten/loose notes, undated (Box 81, Folders 4-7)
    General note
    From green Armagnac box labeled "very old misc. physics" - Aliette Mandelbrot, BBM's widow noted these as being very important to Mandelbrot.
  - IBM directory entry for BBM, undated (Box 322, Folder 3)
  - "Mandelbrot" ephemera - product packaging, undated (Box 322, Folder 5)
  - Webbook vita, undated (Box 322, Folder 4)
- Series 2. Course Work, 1933-
  This series contains Mandelbrot's course work spanning 1933-1957. Included are evaluations, report cards, graded assignments, notebooks and theses. The materials are arranged in chronological order.
  - Evaluations, report cards, awards/honors - Warsaw/Tulle/Paris, 1933-1942 (Box 302, Folder 7)
  - Graded assignments, 1936-1941 (Box 331, Folder 8)
  - Devoir de mathematiques, 1941-1944 (Box 302, Folders 5-6)
  - Dissertation Philosophique, 1942 (Box 302, Folder 8)
  - Caltech term report cards, 1948-1949 (Box 331, Folder 9)
  - Some potential problems arising in the theory of axial turbomachines - In Partial Fulfillment of the Requirements for the degree of Aeronautical Engineer, California Institute of Technology, 1949 (Box 305, Folder 1)
  - Course work - quizzes, notes, circa 1940s (Box 331, Folder 10)
  - School notebooks, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 331, Folder 11)
  - School notebooks, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 332, Folders 1-3)
  - Notes on history, literature and philosophy, circa 1940s-1950 (Box 332, Folders 4-5)
  - Universite de Paris - Livret Universitaire and Carte d'immitriculation, 1940s-1950s (Box 332, Folder 6)
  - Seminaire de Calcul des Probablities - Institut Henri Poincare, 1951 (Box 433, Folder 1)
  - BBM's thesis - Contribution a la theorie mathematique des jeux de communication - Publications de l'institut de statistique de l'universite de Paris, Vol. 2, 1953 (Box 305, Folder 2)
  - Macroscopic Statistical Linguistics - Linguistics 205, Spring 1957, 1933-1950s (Box 332, Folder 7)
- Series 3. Personal Correspondence
  This series contains Mandelbrot's incoming and outgoing personal correspondence. He kept these letters and postcards separate from his work-related correspondence. Correspondents include family members, such as his mother and close friends. The materials are arranged in chronological order.
  - Postcards/letters with family members, 1913-1980, circa 1913-1970s (Box 319, Folders 1-2)
  - Postcards and family souveniers, 1910s-1970s (Box 319, Folders 3-4)
  - "Letters amis" - correspondence from friends, circa 1947-1954 (Box 319, Folder 5)
  - "Letters amis" - correspondence from friends - Leon Trilling, 1950-1952 (Box 319, Folder 6)
  - Personal correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 319, Folder 7)
  - "Letters amis" - correspondence from friends - Aliette Mandelbrot, circa 1950s (Box 319, Folder 8)
  - "Letters amis" - correspondence from friends - D. Carleton Gajdusek, 1954-1955 (Box 319, Folder 9)
  - D. Carelton Gajdusek (Box 468, Folders 1-6)
  - Correspondence with BBM's mother, 1967-1971 (Box 319, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence between BBM, Aliette Mandelbrot and BBM's mother, 1960s-1970s (Box 319, Folders 11-13)
- Series 4. "Mail Files", 1970s-1980s
  This series consists of a box of correspondence Mandelbrot called his "Mail Files." The letters are arranged alphabetically by name or subject and the original order has been maintained.
  - Abrams, Harry N., 1981-1982 (Box 157, Folder 1)
  - Allezaud, Robert, 1980s (Box 157, Folder 2)
  - Armstrong, John A., 1988 (Box 157, Folder 3)
  - Art, 1980s (Box 157, Folder 4)
  - Avnir, David, 1980s (Box 157, Folder 5)
  - Barton, Chris, 1989 (Box 157, Folder 6)
  - Bedford, Tim, 1985-1986 (Box 157, Folder 7)
  - Belin (Paris), 1980s (Box 157, Folder 8)
  - Birkhauser, 1980s (Box 157, Folder 9)
  - Brockman, John, 1980s (Box 157, Folder 10)
  - Florkin, Jean, 1985-1986 (Box 157, Folder 11)
  - Freeman W. H. - brochure excerpts (Box 157, Folder 12)
  - Gallimard Paris (Box 157, Folder 13)
  - Gardner, Martin, late 1970s (Box 157, Folder 14)
  - Hungary - publishers (Box 157, Folder 15)
  - Hurd, A. J. (Box 157, Folder 16)
  - IBM (Box 157, Folder 17)
  - IBM Europe (Box 157, Folder 18)
  - Italy - publishers, 1980s (Box 157, Folder 19)
  - Japan - publishers, 1980s (Box 157, Folder 20)
  - Kadanoff, Leo (Box 157, Folder 21)
  - Kappraff, Jay, 1989 (Box 158, Folder 1)
  - Kaufman, Jane, 1989 (Box 158, Folder 2)
  - Kluwer (Box 158, Folder 3)
  - Kolb, Max, 1986 (Box 158, Folder 4)
  - Landauer (Box 158, Folder 5)
  - McCann, Hugh ( Detroit News) (Box 158, Folder 6)
  - Mendez, Michael, 1980s (Box 158, Folder 7)
  - Moscow - publishers, 1970s-1980s (Box 158, Folder 8)
  - National Geographic (Box 158, Folder 9)
  - Newsweek (Box 158, Folder 10)
  - Office of Naval Research (ONR) (Box 158, Folders 11-12)
  - Peyriere, Jacques, 1970s-1980s (Box 158, Folder 13)
  - Pfeifer, Peter, 1980s (Box 158, Folder 14)
  - Reviews of other fractal books (Box 158, Folder 15)
- Series 5. Professional Correspondence, 1949-2009
  This series documents Mandelbrot's incoming and outgoing professional correspondence. Correspondents include colleagues, collaborators, co-authors and publishers. The material is arranged in chronological order.
  - Professional correspondence - Caltech, 1949 (Box 259, Folder 1)
  - Professional correspondence - publishers, 1950s (Box 261, Folder 8)
  - Professional correspondence - Correspondence regarding Societe Anonyme Philips/Laboratoires d'Electronique et de Physique appliquees, 1950-1951 (Box 259, Folder 2)
  - Professional correspondence - Louis de Broglie, 1952 (Box 259, Folder 3)
  - Professional correspondence - Pierre Grivet, 1952-1954 (Box 259, Folder 4)
  - Professional correspondence - Claude Levi-Strauss, 1952-1954 (Box 259, Folder 5)
  - Professional correspondence - Gaston Bachelard and Georges Darmois, 1952-1955 (Box 259, Folder 6)
  - Professional correspondence - Raoul Husson, 1952-1955 (Box 259, Folder 7)
  - Professional correspondence - MIT faculty - Jerome B. Wiesner and R. M. Fano, 1952-1955 (Box 259, Folder 8)
  - Professional correspondence - positions at Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique, Paris, 1952-1958 (Box 259, Folder 9)
  - Professional correspondence - Herbert A. Simon, 1953-1954 (Box 259, Folder 10)
  - Professional correspondence - G.-A. Boutry, 1953-1954 (Box 259, Folder 11)
  - Professional correspondence - Pierre Guiraud, 1953-1957 (Box 259, Folder 12)
  - Professional correspondence - Warren Weaver (The Rockefeller Foundation); S. N. Alexander (U. S. Department of Commerce, National Bureau of Standards); John Von Neumann (Institute for Advanced Study), 1953-1957 (Box 259, Folder 13)
  - Professional correspondence - Victor Yngve, 1954-1955 (Box 259, Folder 14)
  - Professional correspondence - Charge de Cours de Mathematiques/Membre du Seminaire Jean Piaget, Universite de Geneve, 1955 (Box 259, Folder 15)
  - Professional correspondence - MIT visiting lecturer - Notice of Appointment, 1956 Jul-Aug (Box 259, Folder 16)
  - Professional correspondence - correspondence and contract wiht the European Office, Air Research and Development Command, 1956-1957 (Box 259, Folder 17)
  - Professional correspondence - planned summer schedule - Cornell, 1956-1957 (Box 259, Folder 18)
  - Professional correspondence - appointment to the Faculte des Sciences de Lille, 1957 (Box 259, Folder 19)
  - Professional correspondence - Pierre Beres, 1957-1961 (Box 259, Folder 20)
  - Professional correspondence - J. Wolfowitz, 1958 (Box 259, Folder 21)
  - Professional correspondence - Gevevieve Martin, 1958 (Box 261, Folder 6)
  - Professional correspondence - IBM summer employment, 1958 (Box 259, Folder 22)
  - Professional correspondence - Mandelbrot's visit to IBM Yorktown Heights, 1958 Summer (Box 259, Folder 23)
  - Professional correspondence - Davis Howes, 1958-1961 (Box 259, Folder 24)
  - Professional correspondence - Lille - Geneve, 1958-1961 (Box 259, Folder 25)
  - Professional correspondence - apartment in Paris, 1959 (Box 259, Folder 26)
  - Professional correspondence - John Wiley and Sons (publisher), 1959-1976 (Box 261, Folder 7)
  - Professional correspondence - debate between Mandelbrot and Herbert Simon (correspondence, comments, notes published in the journal Information and Control), 1959-1961 (Box 259, Folders 27-28)
  - Professional correspondence - debate between Mandelbrot and Herbert Simon (correspondence, comments, notes published in the journal Information and Control), 1959-1961 (Box 260, Folder 1)
  - Professional correspondence - R. E. Kalman, 1960 (Box 260, Folder 2)
  - Professional correspondence - associate appointment - Columbia University, 1961 Jan (Box 260, Folder 3)
  - Professional correspondence - David Kahn, 1961 (Box 260, Folder 4)
  - Professional correspondence - Herbert Kohn, 1961 (Box 260, Folder 5)
  - Professional correspondence - John R. Parks, 1961 (Box 260, Folder 6)
  - Professional correspondence - S. Friedman, 1961-1962 (Box 260, Folder 7)
  - Professional correspondence - Lawrence R. Klein, 1961-1962 (Box 260, Folder 8)
  - Professional correspondence - Szolem Mandelbrojt, 1961-1969 (Box 260, Folder 9)
  - Professional correspondence - Harvard, 1962 (Box 260, Folder 10)
  - Professional correspondence - Paul Chalus, 1962 (Box 260, Folder 11)
  - Professional correspondence - Illinois Institute of Technology faculty, 1962 (Box 260, Folder 12)
  - Professional correspondence - Harvard appointment to Visiting Lecture on Economics, 1962 (Box 260, Folder 13)
  - Professional correspondence - John R. Parks (Monsanto Chemical Company), 1963-1964 (Box 260, Folder 14)
  - Professional correspondence - "England and Foreign," 1963-1971 (Box 260, Folder 15)
  - Professional correspondence - Jean-Pierre Kahane, 1964-1967 (Box 260, Folder 16)
  - Professional correspondence - "Arizona/Colorado/Boondocks," 1967-1971 (Box 260, Folder 17)
  - Professional correspondence - IBM relations with France and Italy, 1967-1971 (Box 260, Folder 18)
  - Professional correspondence - J. R. Wallis, 1968-1971 (Box 260, Folder 19)
  - Professional correspondence - U.S. Geological Survey, 1969-1972 (Box 260, Folder 20)
  - Professional correspondence - IBM and Harvard correspondence, memoranda, travel receipts, 1960s (Box 260, Folder 21)
  - Professional correspondence - reprint requests, 1960s (Box 260, Folders 22-23)
  - Professional correspondence - reprint requests, 1960s (Box 261, Folders 1-4)
  - Professional correspondence - permissions to reproduce, 1960s (Box 261, Folder 5)
  - Professional correspondence - P. Levy, circa 1965-1971 (Box 503, Folder 4)
  - Professional correspondence - Advisory Committee to the New York City Health Council, 1960 (Box 261, Folder 9)
  - Professional correspondence - Etienne Gorog, 1967 (Box 261, Folder 10)
  - Professional correspondence - Institute of Mathematical Statistics (IMS) - IBM, 1967-1975 (Box 261, Folder 11)
  - Professional correspondence - National Bureau of Economic Research, 1969-1971 (Box 261, Folder 12)
  - Professional correspondence - publishers, 1960s (Box 261, Folder 13)
  - Professional correspondence - Addison-Wesley Publishing Company (includes discussion of english version of Les Objets Fractals), 1960s-1970s (Box 261, Folder 14)
  - Professional correspondence - Long run dependence requests, 1970 (Box 261, Folder 15)
  - Professional correspondence - IBM letters, 1971 (Box 261, Folder 16)
  - Professional correspondence - IBM letters, 1972 (Box 261, Folder 17)
  - Professional correspondence - talks and papers, 1972 (correspondence with editors and conference organizers, conference information/ephemera) (papers found on top of Mandelbrot's desk at IBM in November 2010) (Box 261, Folder 18)